<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A serious review of presbyters re-ordination by bishops: in a letter written unto a minister in Warwickshire, resolving this case of conscience, whether a minister ordained by presbyters, may with a good conscience be reordained by a bishop, presbyter, and deacon, so that they will declare their ordination to meerly-accumulative, and the man shall not renounce his ordination by it.</title>
            <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80852</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867033</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119323</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240935499</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1084_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208027</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867033</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867033e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80852)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119323)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 161:E1084[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A serious review of presbyters re-ordination by bishops: in a letter written unto a minister in Warwickshire, resolving this case of conscience, whether a minister ordained by presbyters, may with a good conscience be reordained by a bishop, presbyter, and deacon, so that they will declare their ordination to meerly-accumulative, and the man shall not renounce his ordination by it.</title>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Ralph Smith at the sign of the Bible in Cornhill, near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signed and dated at end: the 26th Feb. 1660 .. Zach. Crofton.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 8.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Ordination --  Anglican Communion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Presbyterianism --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119323:1"/>
            <p>A Serious REVIEW OF <hi>PRESBYTERS</hi> RE-ORDINATION BY BISHOPS: In a Letter written unto a Minister in <hi>Warwickshire,</hi> resolving this Case of <hi>CONSCIENCE,</hi> Whether a Minister ordained by Presbyters, may with a good conscience be reordained by a Bishop, Presbyter, and Deacon, so that they will declare their Ordination to be meerly accumulative, and the man shall not renounce his Ordination by it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 4.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Neglect not the gift which thou hast received by the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Ex toto codice biblico, ne apex quidem proferri potest, quo demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stretur, immutabili quadam necessitate, ac Dei ipsius institutione, potestatem ordinandi eo modo competere Episcopo, ut si Minister ab Episcopo Ordinetur ejus vocatio &amp; Ordinatio censeatur rata; sin à Presbytero, quod tunc irrita coram Deo &amp; frustranea sit haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gerhard. Loc. Com. de Minist. Eccles. p. 261.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ralph Smith</hi> at the Sign of the Bible in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:119323:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119323:2"/>
            <head>A SERIOUS REVIEW OF PRESBYTERS Re-ordination BY BISHOPS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot (though unknown to you) but be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with, and afflicted for the sad <hi>dilemma</hi> into which I discern you, as many other faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ministers are reduced by our rising Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates; I have, Sir, received from your friend a Question stated in the form of a <hi>Case of Conscience,</hi> to which you desire my resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; you may, Sir, have the satisfactory determination of much more Learned and Judicious Casuists, than my self; yet seeing you desire them, I dare not withstand my weak conceptions, which God in mercy succeed.</p>
            <p>Sir, your Case is thus stated by your self, and must be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, before it can be resolved.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119323:3"/>
            <p>Whether <hi>a Minister ordained by Presbyters, may with a good conscience be re-ordained by a Bishop, Presbyter, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, so that they will declare their ordination to be meerly accumulative, and the man shall not renounce his ordination by it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, before I give Answer to your Enquiry, I must under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand your terms, which are a little strange, and ambiguous; and so obstructive to a Resolution. And Sir, were I with you, I should demand</p>
            <p>First, Who you mean by <hi>Deacon?</hi> I take it for granted, not a <hi>Scripture-Deacon;</hi> for he is a stranger to our Church, unless under the Name of an Over-seer to the poor; and if she knew him, I find not that he was ever intrusted with the power, or had an hand in Ordination of Ministers; nor can I suppose you mean a Deacon, <hi>in sensu Ecclesiastico,</hi> who is at most but half a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister (though I know no Warrant for it) and is not admitted to Consecrate Wine (though Water) much less to Ordain Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. I must therefore conclude you intend a Deacon, <hi>in sensu Cathedrali,</hi> who is a Presbyter in Office, but <hi>Arch-Deacon</hi> in Hierarchical Order, and presenteth to the Bishop (too common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a * lye in his mouth) the persons to be Ordained, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companieth the Bishop in Imposition of hands.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By <hi>Presbyters</hi> I understand Ministers of the Word and Sacraments, entrusted with the Keyes, Order and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church, and exercising the same <hi>communi concilio,</hi> joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without any single Presbyter promoted into a degree above the rest of his Brethren, and distinguished by the Title of <hi>Bishop,</hi> as a term of honour, or priority in Order.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Ordained,</hi> I understand to intend the Solemn ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission into the Office and Investiture with the Authority of a Minister of the Gospel, unto the administration of Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; and all Pastoral duties in and to Christ his Church; which was done with fasting and prayer, and imposition of hands, and so by <hi>Re-ordained,</hi> I must understand a passing under the same formalities which are appointed for such admission and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vestiture.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119323:3"/>
            <p>Fourthly, By <hi>Renouncing his ordination (viz.</hi> that former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received) I conceive you intend it to relate unto the mans <hi>mind and mouth,</hi> so as that he that is <hi>Re-ordained,</hi> doth in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self <hi>intend,</hi> and <hi>verbally declare,</hi> not to renounce or depart from the force and Authority of his Ordination, or make voide the Office, Admission, and Investiture formerly received: which yet I doubt, is really (at least <hi>in f<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro Ecclesiae</hi>) done by the Act of Re-ordination.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, What do you mean by their declaring of their Re-ordination to be <hi>meerly accumulative?</hi> its proper and genuine signification is, an <hi>adding, augmenting, encreasing the heap and store,</hi> and making it to run over, and improperly, it signifieth a <hi>multiplication and addition</hi> of things or actions unto the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease and perfection of what is already <hi>lawful and sufficient,</hi> but capable of greater measure, degree, and perfection; and is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from <hi>Repetition or Reiteration</hi> of the same words or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, being a confluence of new and different things, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the augmentation of the same subject; and therefore I think cannot be well predicated of <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> which is rather a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iteration of the same Act and Administration, than any new Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I should enquire whether the <hi>Accumulation</hi> they will declare when they Re-ordain, be predicated of the <hi>Agent</hi> Accumulating, or the <hi>Subject</hi> Accumulated: If of the First, then it means that they will <hi>freely, most willingly ordain</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of <hi>Cicero, Ʋt pro tuo in nos Officio, &amp; nostro in te studio munus hoc Accumulatissime voluntati tuae largiamur.</hi> And if by this fallacy our Prelates can make men willing to be Re-ordained, they may well declare their Act to be <hi>most accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;</hi> for I am jealous they love and long to be thus <hi>accumulating</hi> their Canonical Clergy, though by the sinful defections of such whom they can seduce, and will insult over: But if it be meant of the last, <hi>viz. the subject accumulated,</hi> the most charitable sence in which we can understand it, is, that they will <hi>Reiterate Ordination</hi> with some difference in the manner thereof, but it is <hi>Redundant, and no way necessary,</hi> without which you were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>sufficiently a Minister:</hi> and that will seem <hi>irrational,</hi> and <hi>accumulative</hi> against the Reformed Churches and Religion, more
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119323:4"/> than advantage them, proving like the Lawyers Accumulation of Suits and Actions against a man Arrested; in which sence <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepinus</hi> doth thus describe it out of <hi>Zasius, Cumulatio est pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um rerum vel actionum coacervatio contra eundem in judicio le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitime proposita.</hi> And such Accumulation is to be dre<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, lest it bring us under the guilt of Accumulating in <hi>Aret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his sence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aretius com. in</hi> 2 Tim 4 3.</note>
               <hi>Sine Judicio &amp; temere quaevis obvia accumulare;</hi> which will be much below us as men, much more as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, and Lastly, What do you mean by <hi>a good conscience?</hi> I shall not stand Critically to observe goodness of conscience, <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad honestatem,</hi> or <hi>quietem;</hi> well knowing, the one attends the other, as the cause and effect; but would enquire after it, <hi>quoad firmitatem vel infirmitatem,</hi> its strength or weakness, and so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre its goodness to this particular Act; for I should be loth to deny that mans conscience to be <hi>generally and ordinarily good,</hi> which may not be <hi>so good</hi> as to guide him in, and guard him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such a <hi>Dilemma,</hi> wherein the distress of his condition may distemper his mind, and darken his judgement, that it directs him not, or at least doth not conscientiously awe him to follow his direction; but that he yieldeth to that sinful Act, which may afterward create him sorrow, and wound his conscience to the check of all his comforts.</p>
            <p>Your Question, Sin, stated, and the terms of it thus explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I must profess that if any (as too many) be induced to be Re-ordained by Bishops who have heretofore been Ordained by Presbyters, I wish they were so wary and prudent, as to do it with some such explicite cautions and explications; which although they must needs bespeak the weaknesses of such as subject there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, yet would bear some witness to the truth and Order which by such Re-ord<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iners are designed to be, if possible, obliterated and exploded; but Sir, how fair soever are their pretences and persw<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sions, I do not believe that any of them will Ordain on any such terms: I could tell you a Story of some well known (whose names, for reverence to them, I conceal) who came to <hi>Thomas de Candida Casa</hi> the Excommunicate Scotch Bishop, and demanded Ordination, with some such Declaration as you suggest to salve their Re-ordination, but received this present re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119323:4"/>
               <hi>Keep your sence and intention to your selves, for what do you tell me of them? if you desire to be ordained, I will or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain you:</hi> And yet this Journey-man Consecrator is well known to be more found and sober, than most of the present English Prelates. But could this be admitted and assured to us, that you might make such protests publickly, and have them entred on Record, yet Sir, my judgment and most serious thoughts do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve your enquiry in the Negative thus <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <q>A Minister Ordained <hi>(i. e.)</hi> [Solemnly admitted into, and invested with the Office of a Minister of the Gospel of Christ] by Presbyters [lawful, but ordinary Ministers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom none is dignified with the gradual Title <hi>Bishop</hi>] cannot with a good conscience [rightly informed, and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acting the man unto the discharge of duty, and obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of peace] be Re-ordained by a Bishop, Presbyter, and Deacon [Arch-Deacon, all lawful Presbyters] not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding [himself intend, and do verbally declare not to] renounce his first Ordination, and the Re-ordainers do declare their Re-ordination to be meerly Accumulative, and an Act Redundant, and no way needful.]</q>
            <p>Sir, such Re-ordination, notwithstanding such Cautions, is very ridiculous, and must, in my apprehension, be very irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and irreligiously demanded, and accordingly subjected un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to without any regard unto right Reason, or the righteous institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an holy God, and so unsutable to men, and then much more inconsistent to the good conscience of Ministers of God, who are or ought to be men rectified by Art, and replenished with grace, bespeaking the seriousness of their spirits, by their actions, no less than by their express'd words. In sence hereof, I sh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll desire your serious consideration of these two things, which m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y help to clear your mind, and est blish your heart in a matter of great moment, however some esteem it.</p>
            <p>Fi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st, <hi>Re-ordination</hi> (like Re-baptization) properly so called (<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in your e<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se it must be) <hi>is a plain Solecisme</hi> in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Christianity; neither to be taught, nor Acted in Christs Church, without preposterous levity, ridiculous vanity, and palpable prophaneness, never owned, nor allowed, practised,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119323:5"/> or pleaded for, in the Church of God, untill our sinful, shameful self-deceiving dayes, interpreting words and actions according to our own lust and will, contrary to their natural, genuine, known, and received signification. I pray Sir, enquire and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve in what place, or Age of the Church was it demanded, or admitted, that <hi>Ordination was judged valid,</hi> and Accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively Reiterated? It cannot be unknown to you, that the Church hath had much Controversie, and many hot Contests a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Ordination to the Ministery differently administred;</hi> but when, where, or which of them did differ, disagree, or doubt of this position, <hi>viz.</hi> [That Ordination which is valid by the essentials thereof, though irregular in point of Order and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance, and unlawfully taken up, or administred, yet ought not to be Reiterated!] What Council, Father, yea Pope or Bishop, did ever pronounce a <hi>validitie</hi> in Ordination, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired the men to be Re-ordained? Is not Re-ordination, on this distinction, <hi>viz.</hi> [your Ordination is <hi>lawful</hi> before God and the Church, but not <hi>legal,</hi> according to the Order of the Nation] the novellous fancy of our late monstrously exacting Bishops? The many debates concerning the <hi>Ordination</hi> of <hi>Arrian, Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and donatist Bishops, is no less obvious, than those of <hi>Re-baptization;</hi> yet when, or where was it judged, that they should be Re-ordained? The Fathers <hi>particularly,</hi> and they convened in the Council of <hi>Nice, collectively</hi> did enquire concerning their <hi>validity, and nullity,</hi> and having determined them valid, they Decreed,<note place="margin">Concil. Nicen. Can. <hi>19, 27, 57.</hi> Gelaes. Cyzizen. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Actor. Concil.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hands laid upon them, let them remain in their Office:</hi> And more particularly, <hi>Ʋbicun{que} autem sive in vicis, sive in civitatibus ipsi soli inventi fuerint Ordinati qui inveniuntur in clero, in eodem ordine permaneant:</hi> Giving direction for the preheminence of the Catholick, above the <hi>Heretically ordained Bishops;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theoderet. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiast. Hist. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and directing a <hi>Confirmation</hi> of them that were so Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and so giving them an <hi>indulgence or Licence,</hi> to Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and exercise the Office they had received: never requiring them to be <hi>re-ordained,</hi> or advising others to <hi>re-ordain</hi> them: Although it's true, <hi>Jansenius</hi> would inferre it from their <hi>accepta manuum impositione,</hi> receiving the laying on of hands, yet he doth not understand <hi>Re-ordination properly so called,</hi> but <hi>first or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> supposing, what they had received, was <hi>null and voide;</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119323:5"/> and he is very abundantly, and clearly answered by <hi>Voetius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Voetius <hi>despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata causa Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patios,</hi> lib. 2. Sect. 2. cap. 14. pag. 198.</note> who well noteth that their <hi>imposition of hands,</hi> was the note of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence extended to them as <hi>paenitentiaries</hi> after their fall, which might be repeated. Not any act of Ordination which could not be reiterated: and well observeth the Councel judged them <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatos,</hi> and directeth that they should <hi>in Clero manere:</hi> And therefore confirmation of the Orthodox Bishops did not <hi>clerica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ordinem,</hi> or <hi>potestatem conferre, sed usum &amp; ordinis exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citium concedere,</hi> and <hi>primam vocationem ad ordinem vel cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricatum confirmare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Sir, the difference in and about the way of Ordination, used in the <hi>Greek</hi> from that of the <hi>Latin Church</hi> did occasion no lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle strife: yet the question was whether that Ordination were not <hi>void and null,</hi> and so they who passed under it, were to be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, as being yet <hi>without office or authority?</hi> not whether though their <hi>Ordination were valid,</hi> they should be <hi>reordained?</hi> upon which case Pope <hi>Caelestinus</hi> the third, doth exactly distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish between the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>ordinare iterum ordinare, reordinare</hi> and <hi>confirmare, ipsum ordinem conferre,</hi> and <hi>supplementum adjunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ad ordinis exercitium;</hi> between <hi>officium ingredi, intrare</hi> and <hi>in officio permanore, Reordination</hi> and <hi>liberty of exercise:</hi> and doth in this case direct the Archbishop of <hi>Hydruntinum</hi> (the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan See of <hi>Apulia) utrum reordinandus sit, an sine peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo animae suae in sic recepto ordine debeat celebrare addito si quid noverit in supplemento ordinis adjungendum;</hi> so that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the danger of damnation for administring without au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and office, will (according to him and truth) direct reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</p>
            <p>Ancient Ecclesiastical Canons do direct many things to make Ordination valid, as that it be done by a <hi>Bishop in his own Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess without Symony, that he be Orthodox,</hi> in communion with the Church, and the like, but it never directeth <hi>proper reordination;</hi> but in such cases determineth a <hi>nullity</hi> of the Ordination in such points <hi>faulty and defective:</hi> and yet when such cases have chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and fallen under consideration, the c<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nonists, Schoolmen, and Popish Casuists themselves have concluded <hi>a validity in such Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> unlawfully received and conferred; yea if it be done by a Bishop degraded, and excommunicated, yet some of them deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it to be valid; and conclude against all <hi>reordination</hi> where
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119323:6"/> they can judge a validity, notwithstanding the apparent irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities thereof. <hi>Haeretici Episcopi verum ordinem conferunt, si cum debita intentione formam Ecclesiae servant; conferre possunt de facto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Richard.</hi> de Media villa, distinct. <hi>25.</hi> Artic. <hi>1.</hi> quaest. <hi>2.</hi> dist. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>non tamen de jure, &amp; sic recipere potest Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ab haereticis ministris &amp; praecisis, ab Ecclesia valida esse, si alia necossaria adsint, propositio est de fide.</hi> Swarez. <hi>Degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio non potest omnem usum auferre, nam sacerdos degrada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus potest consecrare, &amp; Episcopus degradatus ordinare, licet peceent gravissime id facientes.</hi> Tolet. <hi>de degradatis.</hi> And the Cannons called Apostolical damn re-ordination in a proper sence, as profane and intolerable, <hi>Si quis Episcopus, aut Presbyter, aut Diaconus secundam ab aliquo ordinationem susceperit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. Apost. 67</note>
               <hi>deponitur tam ipse qui ipsum ordinavit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is, Sir, most apparent that the great controversie between the Papists and Protestants is concerning the <hi>nullity</hi> or <hi>validity</hi> of their Ordination as it is expressely stated by our learned <hi>Morton, non de differentia omni,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cathol Apollo. part. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>33.</hi> pag. <hi>96, 97.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>sed de differentia ordinis, seu potestate ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di quaestio est instituenda;</hi> the question is not of every <hi>differing circumstance,</hi> but of the <hi>different power ordaining:</hi> hence the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent charge and loud clamours of the Papists is, <hi>ordinationes Protestantium sunt mere laicae,</hi> the <hi>Ordinations</hi> of the Protestants are <hi>by meere lay persons,</hi> who have no power to Ordaine, and therefore are <hi>void and null;</hi> and so by the <hi>nullity of the Ministry</hi> they designe, yea openly determine the <hi>non entity</hi> of all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, against which the <hi>entity</hi> of our Churches, and <hi>validity</hi> of our Ministry is strongly and learnedly defended by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arnab. ce Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisteaio Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae sacro sancto lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deel. ad Turria Sophis. R<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>spon. pars <hi>1. Boetius</hi> desperata causa <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>apatus.</note>
               <hi>Sadeel,</hi> and <hi>Voetius</hi> among forraign, and <hi>Raynolds, Jewel,</hi> Archdeacon <hi>Mason,</hi> Bishop <hi>Morton, Davenant</hi> and <hi>Pilkington</hi> with many others of our own judicious sincerely Protestant Divines: but neither the one nor the other did so much as dream of a re-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, <hi>accumulative reiteration</hi> of the same Ordination alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy valid, though irregular: when the Bishops of <hi>England</hi> were to Consecrate Bishops for <hi>Scotland,</hi> though it was debated whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet the Scotch-men were Ordained, and some hot-spur Prelates would needs judge <hi>a nullity of their Ordination,</hi> because done by <hi>Presby<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers only,</hi> yet our Arch-bishop <hi>Bancroft</hi> over-ruled them, and determining their Ordination valid, did not, nor durst admit their re-ordination.</p>
            <p>However our late renowned <hi>Ʋsher</hi> is reported to have judged
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119323:6"/> Ordination by Presbyters without a Bishop (where he might be had) to be schismatical, I am sure he never advised, nor would have allowed a <hi>reordination;</hi> nor was it ever enjoyned to be done by our Church, that <hi>a Popish Priest converted to our Religion, should be reordained;</hi> judging the corrupt Ordination received in <hi>Rome</hi> to be valid. However our now Cassandrian Bishops, may be grown so Jesuitical, as to drive on their <hi>Rome</hi>-reconciling designe, by the false interpretations, and fallacious distinctions of such, as are so <hi>foolish,</hi> or rather <hi>faithlesse to God and his Church,</hi> as to deceive themselves by them; and in words to professe what is directly contrary to the action they administer, cheating men into a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to what they think to decline; and pretend <hi>accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> to reiterate the <hi>Ordination</hi> they judge already valid: yet it is evident to any intelligible observer, and will (I doubt) be too soon visible and sensible, that they intend nothing lesse, whilst the <hi>Divine right</hi> they desire to accumulate to their <hi>Hierarchy;</hi> the making of the holy hands of their Bishops <hi>essential</hi> to Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the constituting of a <hi>Canonical Clergy</hi> under sworn obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Ordinary; and <hi>unchurching</hi> of the Reformed Churches in order to their Union with <hi>Rome,</hi> doth speak nothing more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than the nullity of <hi>their Ministry</hi> whom they pretend to reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, otherwise methinks they should at least deale in <hi>re-ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> that are manifest, what they do in <hi>re-baptization</hi> doubtful; <hi>If thou be not ordained, I ordaine thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can we imagine men, especially Ministers, to be so ignorant of the nature of <hi>Ordination,</hi> as not to know it cannot be reiterated; things and actions which create <hi>relation, honour, or office</hi> cannot be reiterated: The married cannot be re-married without vanity; did not the running to a minister, after the supposed Justice of the Peace had done his appointed do, resolve the Justices act to be <hi>no marriage:</hi> or do any of his Majesties <hi>Knights</hi> think they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Olivers</hi> Dubbing <hi>reiterated,</hi> and that they really enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that honour before His Majesties Royal Act conferred it? yet <hi>Ordination</hi> (though a piece of Church polity, and Ecclesiastick Order, and as such to be kept from all Reiterating contempt) is more than these; for it is <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> though mans admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration, done <hi>in his Name and Authority,</hi> not to be made prophanely common by groundless contemptible Reiteration; <hi>Constituting an Officer</hi> between God and his people; <hi>conferring
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119323:7"/> the Power and Authority</hi> of dispencing the holy things of God, and mysteries of salvation; <hi>actually</hi> and solemnly <hi>investing</hi> with an <hi>Office, Honour, and Authority,</hi> which can be no more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterated without palpable prophaneness, than Baptisme. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but wonder, that those who are so zealous for the reverence of Baptisme, that they will scarce Reiterate it after a Lay person, or Midwife, should have so little regard for Ordination on which the very Esse of Baptism doth depend.</p>
            <p>Sir, to winde up this Consideration, I must be free to tell you, that Re-ordination (in the sence your case must intend it) is a most ridiculous fancy, notorious fallacy, and false interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, never known in the Church under all the Controversies, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Churches Ministry, not rationally (to any intelligent man) to be <hi>required</hi> by any that design not to delude the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor <hi>subjected to</hi> by any who intend not to the keeping of a Living, or gaining some preferment to cheat their consciences, and expose their Ministry, with Gods Church, and true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to scorn, contempt, and ruine: And if this can be done with a good conscience, judge you. I conclude it must have considerates, cautions, and weighty provisoes and salvoes to make it so much as a Question, or case of Conscience. I see your case could not make the enquiry naked, lest it should have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected with shame.</p>
            <p>But, Reverend Sir, the second thing I desire to offer to your consideration, is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The salvoes in your case supposed</hi> (though the most probable and specious that can be provided) <hi>will not avail to prevent the prophaneness and sin that is obvious in Re-ordination;</hi> for that they are manifestly fallacious, and inconsistent with that sence, and signification, they seem to bear, and Men (in a <hi>Dilemma</hi>) are willing to suppose they will admit.</p>
            <p>Which will appear plainly, if we consider the nature of them. And first</p>
            <p>Suppose your Bishop, with his Cathedral Colleagues, shall condescend to declare their Re-ordination to be <hi>meerly accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative,</hi> their Declaration is so <hi>ambignous,</hi> that it cannot be easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly understood, either as I have noted it must be such in respect, of <hi>themselves ordaining,</hi> and then indeed there may be a truth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119323:7"/> in what they declare; but this will not relieve your case; for they professing a Bishop <hi>essential</hi> to Ordination, are willing by a <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> to put a nullity on the Ordination made without him, if any will be deceived by the word <hi>accumulative,</hi> to submit unto, and receive it.</p>
            <p>If (as it must be understood in your case) it be intended of the <hi>subject ordained,</hi> then this Declaration is plainly <hi>false</hi> (which a Jesuited spirit will not stick to pronounce, if fools will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with a sound of words, which signifie no such thing as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by them;) and so the very end of speech (the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the mind) is most abhominably perverted, and judge you how this can be done with a good conscience.</p>
            <p>Sir, <hi>Re-ordination</hi> will (on serious thoughts) appear no <hi>accumulation,</hi> and where is then your salvo? I say,<note place="margin">Re-ordination accumulateth not.</note> it is no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulation, <hi>in the act and formality</hi> thereof, because it is a <hi>repetition, a reiteration of the same act,</hi> whereas a formal accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation is an <hi>access of different acts to the same end;</hi> as in a Rhetorician a multiplying of <hi>different words</hi> to express the same thing, in whom a <hi>repetition of the same words</hi> would be judged <hi>vain babling:</hi> So in a Lawyers suit, it is bringing many Actions to the confinement of the same Prisoner, secured by one, in whom the reiterating the same plaint, must be judged a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, malicious vexation. In riches and honour, it is not tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling over the same heap, and mumbling over the same Titles that doth accumulate, this is <hi>childish toying with them;</hi> there must be in accumulation an access of new matter to that which is <hi>full without it,</hi> and different acts <hi>to the end,</hi> which needeth them not.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, will you please to tell me, or your self, what new act is done in your Re-ordination? It is true, there is an access of <hi>different persons, and rites,</hi> which are meer circumstances, and adde nothing, but the <hi>act</hi> in the nature of it, is the same which was done before; what is the act of your Bishop, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, and Deacon, but a solemn separating of you to the work of the Ministry? <hi>Missio solemnis in possessionem honoris,</hi> saith <hi>Tarnovius.</hi> That by which <hi>committitur in nomine &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co Dei ab ordinatoribus cura gregis dominici,</hi> saith <hi>Hunnius:</hi> By which <hi>Authoritas coram ecclesia tribuitur,</hi> saith <hi>Chemnitius.</hi> Let the Bishops themselves tell us, whether their <hi>ordering of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119323:8"/> Priests,</hi> be any thing else, but the <hi>Ministerial creation of an Officer in Christs Church,</hi> solemn investiture of a person with the <hi>power and authority of dispencing the mysteries</hi> of salvation; and hath not this been done by the Ordination of Presbyters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Bishop? Deny it who can, or dare, and yet speak God's mind: And then Sir, where is your accumulation? Different Rites and Modes may attend one and the same action: If a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer bring the same action by Bill, Plaint, Information, Inditement, or Presentment, it is still but the same action; let the Prisoner dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge one, he dischargeth all.</p>
            <p>As, Sir, your Re-ordination is not accumulative in the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of the act,</hi> so it accumulateth not <hi>any effect</hi> to your Ministry, or your self in your Ministry; which if it did, we might the better admit the term in an improper sence. If it adde or augment any thing to your Ministry, it must be in one of these three Respects. The
<list>
                  <item>Validity</item>
                  <item>Liberty</item>
                  <item>Dignity</item>
               </list> thereof.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, it accumulateth nothing to the <hi>validity of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry:</hi> Which, if it could do, you not only might with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science be Re-ordained, but could not with a good conscience decline or refuse it; but Sir, your Ministry is not <hi>capable of such accumulation;</hi> essentials cannot be accumulated, they must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre <hi>simul &amp; semel;</hi> either you are, or are not <hi>a Minister of Jesus Christ,</hi> an <hi>Officer</hi> in his Church, <hi>Embassadour authorized</hi> to transact and seal the Covenant of salvation between God and his people. The formality of the function and order admits not <hi>majus and minus,</hi> as may the qualification of the subject. The Question in the Church (as I have before noted) hath ever been of the simple, and positive <hi>nullity; or validity of the Ministry;</hi> no degrees of the Office being enquirable; and if, Sir, your <hi>Re-ordination</hi> shall be accumulative to the validity of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, that accumulation must be of an <hi>exceeding operative, and extensive influence,</hi> that it may make up the defects of your ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptizing, and administring the Lords Supper, and ministration between God and immortal souls; for the validity of these de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119323:8"/> on, and is sutable to the validity of your Office and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Take heed this fancied accumulation do not accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>rebaptization,</hi> nay <hi>Church annihilation,</hi> and make <hi>Rome</hi> run over with <hi>English</hi> Proselytes.</p>
            <p>If, Sir, your Ministry, in point of the validity thereof, were capable of accumulation, yet what can a Bishop (much less an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> Bishop) advanced above, and distinct from a Presbyter, adde unto your Ordination?</p>
            <p>Let it, Sir, be observed</p>
            <p n="1">1. That (our very enemies being judges) <hi>Presbyters</hi> may in ease of necessity, nay convenience, <hi>ordain,</hi> and their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination is so <hi>valid, and sufficient,</hi> that no act was ever judged able to accumulate thereunto: We cannot be ignorant of the Authority admitted to, and acknowledged in the <hi>Chorepiscopi,</hi> who were no more than <hi>ordinary Presbyters;</hi> and that it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally pleaded, that in the vacancy of a Bishop, and where he cannot be had, Presbyters may, and must ordain; That the Church do not perish through want of Ministers; And (were we minded to lay hold on necessity) it is in your case most evident, <hi>the Bishops</hi> were suspended <hi>by Authority of Parliament,</hi> exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from their places, some of them imprisoned, some exil'd or dead, all interdicted (by a lawful Authority, not to be diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed) from giving Orders: another Power erected, by the just (though not full) Authority of our Nation, so as that they could not in safety Ordain, or men be Ordained by them; either they must (for at the best a punctilio of Order) have disobeyed Authority, and hazarded their Liberties, (which as no <hi>good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> could then have required, so it cannot now by an <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary accumulation</hi> rebuke the not so doing) or be Ordained as they were.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, not to be beholding to Prelatical Concessions, let it be observed</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ordination hath been given in the Church of Christ by Presbyters without Bishops, yet the accumulative Re-ordination of the Bishop was never dreamed of, or demanded, to adde to the validity thereof.</hi> The Scripture tells us of <hi>Timothy</hi> his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by the <hi>laying on of the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> but is so farre from mentioning the <hi>accumulative re-ordination</hi> of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop to make that valid, that it no where vouchsafeth that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119323:9"/> to them, as to Record one Ordination by a person so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, and as such acting: We read indeed of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> hands laid on <hi>Timothy,</hi> but whether by way of <hi>conveighance of some extraordinary gift,</hi> or <hi>conferring the Office of his Ministry,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains controverted; but that it was not by way of <hi>confirmation, or accumulation,</hi> to the validity of what the Presbytery had transacted is agreed by all; and be it what it will, that it was <hi>Apostolical,</hi> not (in our Prelates sence) <hi>Episcopal,</hi> must needs be acknowledged by all: I cannot but much approve of <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius</hi> his Note, which he makes upon this passage, <hi>viz. Non tantum dicit mearum manuum impositione</hi> 1 Tim. 4. <hi>ne existi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metur discrimen sive ab Apostolis, sive a Presbyteris quis ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chemni. Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Concil. Trid. de Sacra. Ordi. p. <hi>226.</hi>
               </note> Attributing (as to this act) to all Presbyters, an equality of power, and validity to that of the Apostles: There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more plainly reported in Ecclesiastical History, or the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Fathers, than that <hi>ordinations by Presbyters</hi> have been <hi>acted,</hi> allowed, and by some Councils directed. In <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 780. <hi>in</hi> Eph. 4.</note>
               <hi>Per totum Aegyptum, si desit Episcopus, consecrat Presbyter,</hi> saith <hi>Augustine.</hi> And <hi>Consignant Presbyteri, si prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sens non sit Episcopus,</hi> saith <hi>Ambros.</hi> And the ordinations of the <hi>Scots</hi> before they had any Bishops in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> cannot be denied; nor yet the known and defended constant course of the <hi>Reformed Churches beyond the Seas;</hi> and yet it was never known, that ever Bishops Re-ordination was advised; nor hath it been yet asserted, that their <hi>act</hi> could, or was neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to <hi>accumulate</hi> the least unto the <hi>validity of their Ministry,</hi> most earnestly pleaded for, and vigorously defended by our own Prelates whilst truly Protestant.</p>
            <p>If our prompt Accumulators shall tell us, that the ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Coluthus</hi> his Presbyters in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> was by a Council <hi>declared null, and the ordained were returned into the order of Laicks,</hi> I should Reply, It was not because <hi>he and other Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters did ordain them, sine Episcopo,</hi> but because they were ordained by him, who being <hi>infamis ambitione,</hi> made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self <hi>Episcopum imaginarium,</hi> and so ordained them; and the Decree of the Council doth suggest so much, when it decreeth <hi>Ʋt se pro Presbytero haberet qualis ante fuisset;</hi> and then it concludeth more against the Ordination <hi>Episcopo solo</hi> especially, he usurping and ordaining without the Election of the Church (as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119323:9"/> was <hi>Ischyras,</hi> whose ordination occasioned so much trouble) than ag<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inst Presbyters ordaining <hi>sine Episcopo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>intrinsecal power of ordination is in Presbyters as such,</hi> and no way <hi>in Bishops</hi> otherwise then as they are <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> and not at all as they are <hi>Bishops,</hi> which is at most but <hi>a gradual promotion,</hi> framed by <hi>humane prudence,</hi> and distinct from Ministerial <hi>Order and Office</hi> created by <hi>Gods Ordinance;</hi> it must (in despight of all contrary Opponents) be acknowledged <hi>Episcopi &amp; Presbyteri una est ordinatio, uter{que} enim est sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos;</hi> that Bishops and Presbyters are <hi>ejusdem ordinis, &amp; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis,</hi> is a truth which hath shined with that brightness, that even those (the very Papists) whom it most concerneth, cannot deny it, and it hath by our late (unhappy to be abhorred) chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, of <hi>divine right</hi> of Episcopal difference from <hi>Presbytery,</hi> been written so legibly, that (almost) all men may run and r<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad it.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Laudenses</hi> of our Age will yet presume to contend for the <hi>different order and office of a Bishop</hi> in any thing more than degree, <hi>by divine right enjoying an Authority,</hi> I should advise them to <hi>install Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> in their Cathedral Seas, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop'd by Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> and <hi>contradict</hi> the Catalogue of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Witnesses of all sorts, and in all Ages from the time of Christ and his Apostles to our d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes, who are all produced and proved no less Heretic<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l in this point, than <hi>Aerius himself,</hi> collected by the s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me Author: And <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a Bridle to their impudence, call to mind the grave, and publick check given (at <hi>Oxford</hi> by the Learned Dr. <hi>Holland, Regius</hi> professor in that University) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their grand Patron Arch-Bishop <hi>Laude,</hi> who (in his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity exercise for his degree) starting this Notion, was openly rebu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed as a <hi>seditious person; who by a novel Popish Opinion, would unchurch all the Churches beyond the Seas; and sow division between them and us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, <hi>no Bishop as Bishop,</hi> hath the power of Ordination, for, if he had, so farre must his <hi>single Ordination, alone, and without Presbyters,</hi> be, from a crime (<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s it w<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s complained of, and charg<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d on <hi>Chrys<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stome;</hi> and as which it hath been interdicted by more Councils than one;) th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t he must needs be <hi>essential</hi> to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>ordinare,</hi> to make it <hi>valid,</hi> and no Presbyters may without prophaneness accompany him in the act, they must be <hi>all</hi> Bishops,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119323:10"/> and <hi>only</hi> Bishops who do ordain, which none but Bedlam Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines will once affirm. If then Bishops ordain by the same intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secal power, and Authority, and no other, which is in the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, who have already ordained, by what can their act accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the validity of Ordination?</p>
            <p>It must, Sir, be remembred, that the power of Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is <hi>originally, formally, and by Gods institution</hi> in the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> but by mans <hi>limitation, restriction, and self-devised poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> hath been placed <hi>in Bishops,</hi> not <hi>officij,</hi> but <hi>honoris causa;</hi> and what validity, a point of <hi>humane order, or honour,</hi> can add to <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> judge you: For I must subscribe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of the profound <hi>Gerhard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Loc. Com. de mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist. Ecclesiast. p. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>61.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Ex toto codice biblico ne <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pex quidem proferri potest quo demonstretur immutabili quadam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitate, ac ipsius Dei institutione, potestatem ordinandi eo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do competere Episcopo, ut si Minister ab Episcopo ordinetur, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus vocatio &amp; ordinatio censeatur rata; sin à Presbytero, quod tunc irrita coram Deo, &amp; frustranea sit habenda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Truly Sir (were it not for offending our present ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Prelates, who can very ill brook any cloud to their honour) I should be bold to affirm, <hi>a Presbytery</hi> may better accumulate <hi>to the validity of the ordination made by a Bishop</hi> (so farre as it is capable of such accumulation) than <hi>a Bishop</hi> can accumulate to the <hi>Ordination of Presbyters without him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When, Sir, I consider the <hi>honourable mention</hi> made of <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> (in reference to this very act) in Scripture, wholly silent of the Bishops <hi>sole and single power,</hi> unless <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> can be re-install'd, which (notwithstanding the bold assertions sounded in our late <hi>consecrating Sermons</hi>) will be <hi>ad grac<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendas.</hi> When I observe <hi>the Commission</hi> for all administrations between God and his Church to be given to <hi>Presbyters</hi> as such, without the least regard to an <hi>Episcopal order or degree.</hi> When I consider the <hi>general concurrent, and consentient judgment,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Ancient and Modern Writers, Witnessing the <hi>Presbyters first existence</hi> in the Church (as at least the Elder Brother to Episcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) and <hi>acting alone</hi> in the purer and primitive time of the Church, <hi>without, and before Bishops</hi> (in our sence) and that by an <hi>intrinsecal power,</hi> and <hi>immediate institution from God,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Ecclesiastical <hi>Cannon,</hi> or humane <hi>institution,</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appeared to <hi>authorize, or animate</hi> (but only to contract, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119323:10"/> abridge, I had almost said sacrilegiously take away) the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Presbyters; as it hath done the power of Bishops, (<hi>honoris causa</hi> without any warrant from God) farther than <hi>humane poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> will allow it) wherein yet the <hi>prime Authority of Presbyters</hi> was preserved in its lustre, sparkling in these two particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Bishops were created by the Presbyters,</hi> and promoted <hi>in su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorem gradum</hi> by them; (who neither did, nor could create an Officer in Christs Church, whatever power they had to confer the dignity of a <hi>primus Presbyter,</hi> which the effect doth seeme to reflect as an evil.) And this is most evident in all Ecclesiastical story, and the writings of the Fathers, concurrent judgment, &amp; remaining <hi>vestigia</hi> (in <hi>Romes</hi> Cardinals, and <hi>Englands</hi> Dean and Chapter) of this practice among all Christians, both Papists and Protestants; and methinks, cannot be denied by our Cassandrian Prelates, if they remember the instance of Presbyterian Ordination produced out of <hi>Jerom</hi> by our late learned <hi>Ʋsher,</hi> Primate of <hi>Armagh,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his late Majesties demand at the Isle of <hi>Wight; Quod autem postea unus electus est qui caeteris praeponeretur in schismatis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medium factum est, ne unusquisque ad se trahens Christi Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiam rumperet, nam &amp; Alexandriae à Marco Evangelista usque ad Heraclam &amp; Dionysium Episcopos, Presbyteri semper unum ex se electum in excelsiori gradu collocatum Episcopum nominabant, quo modo si exercitus imperatorem faciat aut dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coni eligent de se quem industrium noverint, &amp; Archidiaconum vocent:</hi> or will but consent to the determination of their grand Master of accomodation, <hi>Cassander</hi> himself;<note place="margin">Cassand. lib. Consul. Artic. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Convenit inter om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Apostolorum aetate inter Episcopos &amp; Presbyteros NƲL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LƲM DISCRIMEN fuisse, sed postmodum schismatis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi causa, Episcopum Presbyteris fuisse praepositum, cui chiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonia id est ordinandi potestas concessa est:</hi> so that <hi>Presbyter</hi> had the power of Ordination by <hi>original constitution,</hi> and <hi>Bishops</hi> by the <hi>Presbyters after concession,</hi> and whether the Creator may not by his intrinsecal original power accumulate to the ministerial act of his creature, let wise men judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The power and authority intrinsecally placed, and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally established on the Presbyters, is to them preserv d, by those Canons, that contract their liberty, and concede</hi> honoris causa, <hi>a power to Bishops; so as that the concurrence of Presbyters is made essential to all Acts of Ordination and Jurisdiction.</hi> It
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119323:11"/> cannot be unknown how strictly it was forbidden that Bishops should <hi>ordain, excommunicate, or do any act without their Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters.</hi> That of the Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> is obvious, <hi>Episcopus sine consilio clericorum sucrum clericos non ordinet.</hi> And no less considerable is the constitution of <hi>Ʋrban, Ordinationes factae sine communi sensu clericorum irritae,</hi> and the <hi>complaint</hi> against <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> for <hi>ordaining without Presbyters;</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s <hi>constant practice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epist 33, 34.</note>
               <hi>and careful Apology</hi> to his Presbyters, as afraid of being shent for ordaining <hi>Aurelius</hi> and <hi>Celerinus</hi> (though with his Cathedral Presbyters at hand) with an <hi>hos Fratres dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctissimi</hi>) (not my sworn Vassals) <hi>à me, &amp; Collegis</hi> (not subject Council) <hi>qui praesentes erant, Ordinatos sciatis, quod vos scio libenter amplecti,</hi> doth most clearly manifest the same. I must not stand to multiply evidences, being confined to a Casu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istical discussion; and therefore shall say no more but this, that whosoever will but studiously enquire into, and seriously ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the estate of the Ministers of the Church, established by the Scripture, or exercised in the pure and primitive time of the Church, dazled with the light of this truth, shall be constrained, (as was the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His Letter to Sir K. <hi>Digby.</hi>
               </note> no mean Zealot for our Bishops) to confess, That <hi>they who would reduce the Church to the form of Government thereof in the Primitive times, would be found pecking towards the Presbytery of Scotland</hi> (As we of late were, and by Solemn Covenant stand bound to do in <hi>England) Which</hi> (saith he) <hi>for my part I believe in point of Government, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth nearer than either yours or ours of Episcopacy</hi> to the first <hi>age of Christs Church,</hi> though in a blind and preposterous zeal he sayes <hi>it is never awhit the better,</hi> and may wish Episcopacy <hi>to have been made an Article of the Scotch</hi> (as it is of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish) Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I say, Sir, when I consider this <hi>primacy of Presbyters to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops,</hi> and that Primitive Power, and Authority, found in them, and preserved to them, by the Canons of the Church, placing Prelates in their Chairs; I see not how it can well be denied, that the Ordination of <hi>Presbyters</hi> may rather adde to that by <hi>Bishops,</hi> than that of his, to this of theirs; which for Bishops once to pretend, is a most plain and proud presumption, worthy, at least, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119323:11"/>3. But, Sir, before our <hi>English</hi> Bishops can pretend to accumulate to the Ordinations of Presbyters made by Presbyters without a Bishop, it will be necessary that they <hi>clear and make plain their own Episcopacy.</hi> If they may be censured by the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> or tried by the <hi>Ancient Canons of the Church,</hi> they will find a <hi>non entity of their Episcopacy</hi> determined by the one, and declared by the other. That they, as Bishops, are <hi>no Officers of Christ,</hi> must be confessed; and their <hi>succession</hi> (the only note of the validity of their <hi>Episcopacy</hi>) under the notion of Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical constitution, is so ambiguous and uncertain; nay, the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions thereof</hi> are so legible and manifest, that the v<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lidity of their Episcopacy may admit a most <hi>intricate and perpetual dispute:</hi> And the irregularities of their constitution (without the choice of the Clergy, or consent of the people) their consecration by Heretical, Apostate, and Symoniacal Prelates, and other things, will conclude <hi>a nullity</hi> in them as Bishops; and how then shall they stamp validity upon Presbyters Ordination? Of all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops in the world, our Bishops can make the poorest pretence to the sole (if any) power of Ordination; for that if they ordain not as Presbyters, they have not any Evangelical Ecclesiastical power whereby to do it,<note place="margin">Discourse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the solemn League and Covenant. p. 13.</note> being (as a late Episcopal Divine hath well noted) His <hi>Majesties Lords,</hi> but not <hi>the Churches Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops,</hi> much less <hi>Christ his Officers;</hi> having been promoted by a Clandestine Cathedral choice, and a Royal Act of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties peculiar grace, <hi>Nec plebe nec clero consentiente,</hi> neither people nor Clergy consenting, much less choosing; as was Acted and appointed in the Primitive Churches, and is necessary to the constitution of the Churches Officers; and on that account if any Officers (in the enjoyment of their Dignities and Revenues) yet meerly politick, and having no power <hi>(qua tales)</hi> in, or over the Church, and so can accumulate nothing to the validity of the Ministry of such as at first pass their hands, much less those, who are Ordained by Christ, and his Churches known Officers.</p>
            <p>Sir, these things considered,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Gaudens</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalysis. p. 12.</note> I do not more wonder to see some proud, ambitious Prel<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes, extoll Bishops as the only and <hi>chief Conservators, Cisterns, and Conduits, of all Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Authority and Power, from the very Apostles;</hi> than to find some Presbyters (whom I judged more serious and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119323:12"/> to establish them in an opinion so strange, and false, by their subjecting themselves to their <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> on the self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiving, Church-deluding apprehended accumulation to the <hi>validity of their Ministerial Power and Authority,</hi> which to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine is a fancy and vile absurdity, and to declare is a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious falsity, or cheating fallacy; for that Episcopal Ordination can in no wise iugment or adde unto the validity of the Ministry conferred by the Ordination of Presbyters.</p>
            <p>Though, Sir, your Re-ordination may not accumulate to the <hi>validity</hi> of your Ministry, it is supposed it may to the <hi>liberty</hi> thereof; so as that you may thereby be <hi>capable</hi> of exercising the same in this Nation, and to hold, and obtain any <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Promotion, or Benefice,</hi> or to be thereupon <hi>admitted, instituted, and inducted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This accumulation I inferre from that distinction of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, into <hi>lawful and legal,</hi> which I understand some of our rising Prelates do make in this case, whereby to engage carnal, worldly minds, to continue their outward terrene possessions, or grasp at future preferment, by prophaning the Ordinance of God passed upon them, making it of <hi>none effect,</hi> by prostituting their Ministry to the pride and lusts of men: and likewise from that slight and subtle <hi>Salvo,</hi> some have framed for the quieting their consciences, and satisfying the scandal given to most serious men, by their Re-ordination, which they pretend to take only as <hi>a License to exercise the Office,</hi> they had before received in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. I could, Sir, tell you of some (from whom better things have been expected) who did demand to be thus <hi>licensed</hi> by a Re-ordination, by <hi>Thomas de Candida Casa</hi> (no way in power to ordain, or license, having the Title Bishop, and <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea nihil,</hi> his very relation to the Christian Church being dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table) and when their sence was disowned, and rejected by him, declaring in positive terms, <hi>If they would be ordained, he would ordain them,</hi> yet they prostituted themselves to his Re-ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and defend it by this false and foolish plea, they have only received <hi>a licence to officiate;</hi> an handsome cheat to such as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending conscience towards God, do pursue Gospel Ministry, as the <hi>reward</hi> of their former time and study, or <hi>step</hi> to their future ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and preferment.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119323:12"/>
            <p>But, Sir, not to insist upon the care that ought to be in all men, especially Christian Magistrates, and Church Governours, not by their power to impede, obstruct, limit, or restrain, the Ministry of the Gospel, by subjugating the Authority thereof, to the liberty of exercise which they shall allow; I do believe that the <hi>Christian Magistrates,</hi> or <hi>lawful-rightful-Governours of the Church,</hi> may put <hi>Abiathar</hi> from the Priests Office; abridge any Ministers liberty by way of punishment, for some notorious crime, and interdict his exercising, in whole or in part, the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and Authority, with which he stands invested; but as I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver find it practised by any, save Pagan, or Popish and Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Powers, so to put positive qualifications, and prescribe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Gods Word, a way of ordering, or inaugurating into the Office of Gods appointment, and barre the Gospel from being dispensed otherwise than under such conditions; I question whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it fall much short of the <hi>raging of the people, and tumults of the Heathen,</hi> complained of in <hi>Ac<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I am sure <hi>Moses</hi> was very wary of restraining <hi>Prophecying in God's Camp;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> was so farre from hindering, that he rejoyced, that <hi>Christ was preached,</hi> not only <hi>under disorder,</hi> but <hi>out of envy:</hi> and it is required that all Christians pray, <hi>That the Gospel may have a free passage, and be glorified.</hi> But not to stand on this, I say, Sir,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Re-ordination accumulateth nothing to the liberty of your Ministry:</hi> Not <hi>in general,</hi> to the exercise of it in the world or Church; nor <hi>in special,</hi> to the exercise of it in our Church or Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Re-ordination accumulateth not to the liberty of the <hi>general exercise of the Ministry in the World or Church,</hi> which as it never was from the first coming of the Gospel proposed; so no men have a power or authority to prescribe it, <hi>as a ground of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> or can do it without prophaneness; the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (who were without the Church) cannot do it, and the <hi>Christians</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Church) never did, nor durst do it, under all the debates between the Greek and Latines, Orthodox and Hereticks, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants and Papists, the enquiry was ever, <hi>Whether they were ordained?</hi> and <hi>their ordination void or valid?</hi> and they ever appeared afraid to Re-ordain (in the sence in your case) distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing between the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>ordinare,</hi> and <hi>confirmare;</hi> that Solemn
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119323:13"/> Act which stamped Christ his <hi>authority,</hi> and that political Act, by which they indulged <hi>liberty of exercise,</hi> as I have before obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; for indeed <hi>Gods authority,</hi> is the Key, and only Key of <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> to Gospel Ministry, against which, the door which is bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by humane power or policy, must be broke open by Divine wrath and vengeance. Which of the Prophets demanded liberty on other grounds, than, <hi>Thus saith the Lord?</hi> Which of the Princes (other than proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) ever barred them, with a <hi>What is the Lord? Observe my prescriptions in order to your liberty among my people?</hi> Have not false Teachers pretended to Divine Mission, as the only Picklock to the liberty of their delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion? When our Saviour sent out his Disciples, he sent them with bare authority, naked Ordination, and gave them in charge, that against every house, or City shut against them, they should <hi>shake off the dust from off their feet,</hi> with this severe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement, <hi>It shall be more tolerable for Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note>
               <hi>than for that City:</hi> Heaping up li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to Gods Authority by a Re-ordination of mans invention, is undoubtedly accumulative, <hi>treasuring up wrath against the day of wrath.</hi> Let not men deceive themselves or others, let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Re-ordained, or Re-ordainers, tell me the Age, or Nation, that ever judged men coming in the Name of the Lord, <hi>careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordained, validly invested with Christs authority,</hi> and did require them to be <hi>re-ordained</hi> (in a proper sence) as the Key of their liberty; it is miserable in a case of Conscience to mistake the question.</p>
            <p>Re-ordination accumulateth not the liberty of exercising your Ministry <hi>particularly in this Church and Kingdom.</hi> It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver required or prescribed as a qualification thereunto: Have not many, ordained <hi>else-where, and after a different order than our Church or Kingdom directs,</hi> enjoyed their liberty, nay ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Dignity and Promotion, enjoyed Church-Livings and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices in <hi>England,</hi> and were never required to be Re-ordained? Enquire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cabala. p.</hi> 79. Lord Keepers Letter to the Duke.</note> Sir, after the <hi>Dominican Friar,</hi> who translated our Liturgy into <hi>Spanish</hi> (to promote the accommodation with <hi>Rome,</hi> by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> seeing its symetry to the <hi>Romish</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship) and was secured to our Church by the Bishop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> then Lord Keeper, with <hi>a good Benefice, and a Prebends place to boot,</hi> and many other Priests ordained in <hi>Rome:</hi> I hope Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119323:13"/> of Presbyters is as good, valid, and regular, as that of Papists. And, Sir, enquire among the Dutch and French Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and you shall find Mr. <hi>Hoffeman</hi> within twelve Miles of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and another his Neighbour in <hi>Berkshire</hi> at the same di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, and many others, nay many Scotch men inducted, and instituted, on their Presbyterial Ordination, and were never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be re-ordained. If our Prelates would not be angry, that they were slighted, I could tell them of some honest old Puritans, whose sons went into <hi>Scotland</hi> to be ordained, to avoid their <hi>Oath</hi> (of Vassalage) <hi>to the ordinary,</hi> and yet without other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, were preferr'd in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How cometh Re-ordination to be now, and never before, the reason of our liberty? I am sure Cardinal <hi>Poole</hi> was more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable, who chose rather to shew his holiness Authority, by this confirming, accumulative dispensation, <hi>viz. Ac omnes Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticas, seculares, seu quorumvis ordinum regulares personas, quae aliquas impetrationes, dispensationes, concessiones, gratias indulta, tam ordines, quam beneficia Ecclesiastica, seu alias spirituales materias, praetensa authoritate supremitatis Ecclesiae Anglicanae, licet nulliter &amp; de facto obtinuerunt, &amp; ad cor reversae Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae unitati restitutae fuerint, in suis ordinibus &amp; beneficiis, per nos ipsos, seu à nobis ad id deputatos misericorditer recipiemus, prout jam multae receptae fuerint, secum{que} super his opportune in Domino dispensavimus:</hi> but never required them to be <hi>re-ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> as do our Prelates, in this, more monstruous, than this pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; for that they own <hi>a validity,</hi> and yet will <hi>re-ordain;</hi> what he judged <hi>a nullity,</hi> yet did only <hi>confirm and indulge</hi> by the power of the Church, and procure to be corroborated by an Act of a most Popish Parliament, more sober and serious in this point, than those <hi>Zealots</hi> who moved in the late Parliament, That <hi>all Ordinations without Prelates should be declared void,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Act for restoring Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</note> though the more judicious majority determined <hi>any ordained Ministers, by any Ecclesiastical persons, to be continued in their Livings;</hi> which I hope our Prelates will admit, which no Bishop in <hi>England</hi> dare deny to be lawful, and valid, and profess themselves Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, however they fancy them not <hi>regular, and orderly,</hi> and so <hi>illegal;</hi> supposing, and suggesting, <hi>a Bishop</hi> (by the Laws of our Church and Kingdom) <hi>to be essential</hi> to make a Minister that shall have <hi>institution and induction to any Living,</hi> and so
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119323:14"/> have <hi>Liberty</hi> to exercise his Office, and <hi>Capacity</hi> to take preferment, and Dignity in our Church; Which if it be so,</p>
            <p>I wonder how Arch-bishop <hi>Bancroft</hi> did over-rule his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues, and conferre dignity according to the English order, on the Scotch Presbyters, and not first ordain them?</p>
            <p>How comes a Bishop <hi>to be more essential</hi> to make a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster capable of liberty and dignity <hi>now, than heretofore?</hi> Are not the Laws, Civil and Ecclesiastical, the same they were when Dutch and Scotch Presbyters were promoted, inducted and insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted? I remember no <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> nor <hi>Canons</hi> of the Church since made, save the <hi>Canons</hi> of 1640. which I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess I much wonder provided not for it, the <hi>jus divinum</hi> of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scopacy having obtained that heighth, by which it now operates, (into the Ministry annulling) Reformation, and Reformed-Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es-subverting, <hi>Rome</hi>-accommodating design; being then mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with very great vigour. I hope our Prelates will prove their <hi>Canons</hi> to be consistent with, and Authorized by our Statute Law, before they give us Laws ruling the Church, out of their own breasts.</p>
            <p>I am sure neither the <hi>Statute, nor Canon-Law of England,</hi> doth make a Bishop <hi>essential to ordination,</hi> so as that without him it should be <hi>void,</hi> and the Minister that shall preach, or be inducted and instituted into any Ecclesiastical Benefice and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, should first be <hi>ordained by a Bishop.</hi> I have read again and again the Statute of 13 of Queen <hi>Elizab.</hi> directing institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and induction, and find indeed <hi>subscription</hi> to the Articles, <hi>which only contain the confession of the true Christian Faith, and Doctrine of the Sacraments</hi> (not 39 in number,<note place="margin">Canons 1603.</note> or any concerning Discipline, as the Canons do direct) to be a qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion essential to induction and institution, but <hi>any ordination</hi> to be a capacity and reason of liberty and dignity; the very words of the Statute run thus, <hi>viz. That the Churches of the Queens Majesties Dominions may be served with Pastors of sound Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: Be it enacted by the Authority of this present Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That every person under the degree of a Bishop, which doth, or shall pretend, to be a Priest or Minister of Gods holy Word and Sacraments, by reason of any other form of institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, consecration, or ordering, then the form set forth by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119323:14"/> in the time of King</hi> Edward <hi>the sixth, and now used, shall declare his assent, and subscribe to the Articles, &amp;c.</hi> not, he shall be re-ordained by a Bishop. I observe Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> (that profound Lawyer) telling our Prelates, that their requiring Re-ordination,<note place="margin">In his Epistle added to the unbishoping <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> Reprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Anno</hi> 1660.</note> and refusing, without it, to give institution and induction, <hi>do act expressly against the Law.</hi> And although the ordering of the Priests <hi>according to the book of Edward the sixth,</hi> be corroborated by the Statutes of 5 and 6. of <hi>Edward the sixth, cap.</hi> 1. and 8 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. yet <hi>other Ordination</hi> is not so much as <hi>prohibited</hi> by any negative or exclusive clause, much less is it <hi>irrited</hi> or made void. The thing may be <hi>forbidden</hi> which yet is <hi>valid,</hi> and must not be reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated when done. I hope our Prelates will confesse, <hi>Prohibitio, &amp; irritatio facti, differunt, ut irritatum quod lege fit, lege expri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur necesse est, alias praesumitur, legislatorem voluisse non irritare factum etiam prohibitum:</hi> They cannot be ignorant of the <hi>Lex Cincia</hi> of the Romans, limiting Fees and Gifts, and punishing <hi>donatores largiores,</hi> who gave <hi>ultra mensuram praescriptam,</hi> yet did not <hi>donatum ipsum rescindere;</hi> and therefore the Law nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>prohibiting</hi> other Ordination, nor providing that it should be <hi>ipso facto void;</hi> the lust and pride of men, not the law and power of the Kingdom, lyeth in the way of their Ministry, who were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained without a Bishop, and doth make him accumulative, so necessary to Ordination. For my part, had I a Living to bestow, I should adventure a <hi>Quare impedit</hi> against that Bishop who should deny my Presbyter admission, on this ground, <hi>He is not ordained by a Bishop:</hi> But they will tell me, <hi>Curst Cows have but short horns;</hi> However, I know my liberty, I desire not to have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to try it.</p>
            <p>If any yet fear their liberty to be blocked up by the Canons of (what is called) our Church, let him consider;</p>
            <p>That our Statute-Law provides, that <hi>No Canons or Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions can be put in execution within this Realm by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Convocation of the Clergy</hi> (much less of single Prelates) <hi>which shall be contrariant, or repugnant to the Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Royal, or the Statutes of this Realm:</hi> And let every ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man, in any measure acquainted with our Statutes, judge, whether to <hi>deny institution and induction without Re-ordination,</hi> be not repugnant and contrariant to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm? and to <hi>deny ordination to the unordained, without sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119323:15"/> to their three Canonical Articles,</hi> be not repugnant <hi>to the Statute</hi> confining the subscription <hi>to only a confession of Faith, and Doctrine of the Sacraments;</hi> they adjudge Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and tie up to the number of 39. and so (according to the Lord <hi>Digby</hi>'s wish) make their Hierarchy, and order of it, <hi>Articles of the true Christian Faith?</hi> And whether this be not repugnant and contrariant to His Majesties <hi>Prerogative Royal,</hi> exercised in His late <hi>gracious Declaration</hi> of indulgence <hi>in causes Ecclesiastical,</hi> dispensing with subscriptions of that Nature; and is not this presumption the higher, when acted by <hi>single and particular Bishops,</hi> without the authority of the Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Clergy; but <hi>praemunire</hi> is naturally incident to an <hi>English</hi> Prelate.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, Let him consider <hi>the Canons do no way damm up his liberty;</hi> only those of 1603 do direct the matters of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and institution, and they make <hi>subscription essential to such as come to a Bishop for either,</hi> but do not require all men that will be Ministers, <hi>to come to a Bishop,</hi> and all Bishops <hi>to re-ordain</hi> before they institute, or determine a nullity of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by Presbyters without a Bishop; or debarre the Bishop from instituting and inducting on such a ground; they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so understood or practised, nor indeed can be; but it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary for men to be most <hi>Canonical</hi> in their words and pretences, who are least such in their deeds and practices.</p>
            <p>You see, Sir, that Ordination by Presbyters is not in its own Nature, nor by the Laws of our Church or Kingdom, any barre to the liberty of your Ministry; and in that respect Re-ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on accumulateth not. In vain is it objected, but <hi>it is made, and pleaded</hi> de facto <hi>so to be;</hi> for no defect in Ordination, but a plain excess of ignorance, pride, and prophaneness, is the cause thereof, which if it can wilfully captivate mens consciences in one thing, will soon accumulate burdens not to be borne. If this humour can bring Presbyters under a Bishops Girdle, I wish we do not see it shortly subject Bishops to the Pope, and make <hi>re-consecration</hi> by him as accumulative to them, as <hi>re-ordination</hi> is to Presbyters, for that it is a plain fancy, fomenting nothing but evil, under a feigned advantage. A Master of Arts in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and zealous son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (so called) and desirous that all should receive the Bishops Blessing, said lately to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119323:15"/> a Minister in <hi>London, It would never be well, till the Pope were restored to his Western Jurisdiction here in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>That a fancy of <hi>accumulated liberty</hi> should beguile young and weak Ministers, I do not wonder; but that men, Learned, Acute, and Ingenuous, yea I hope conscientious should (as I know some have done) deceive themselves, into a <hi>re-ordination</hi> by pretence of <hi>taking a Licence to preach, to officiate the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry he had before received,</hi> is to me very strange, and to them (if I mistake not) matter of Repentance, and publick Recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for that <hi>ordination</hi> and <hi>licence</hi> are not <hi>words</hi> more different in their sound and signification, than <hi>things</hi> different in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and use; the one being <hi>an Ordinance of God</hi> done in his immediate Name and Authority, the other <hi>an Order of humane prudence and polity;</hi> the one <hi>creating an Office,</hi> the other <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging an exercise thereof.</hi> What Author, Ancient or Modern, do make Re-ordination and Licence to be Synonimous? What Age or Church did ever confound these two? Doth not the Church of <hi>England</hi> make them different? Is not a Licence di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct from, given after, or before, but apart from Ordination? I wish these men to consider with themselves, Whether if our Prelates soare to the heighth of their power, and summon them according to the Canons, to shew their Licence for officiating, will they think that to produce Letters of Order under the hand and seal of <hi>Thomas de Candida Casa</hi> will satisfie them, and they shall not be constrained to obtain <hi>Letters of Licence</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise their <hi>accumulative re-ordination,</hi> or lose their secured Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of their Ministry? Or do they think that every <hi>Licentiate</hi> Reader of Homilies in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> hath passed the same formalities for a <hi>Licence</hi> which themselves have passed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Re-ordination? It is a poor plea, That they are satisfied in their own judgements, that Re-ordination is no other but a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, when it is no such thing, and they are, after it, as much to seek for a Licence, as they were before.</p>
            <p>I must, Sir, be bold to say, it is a plain cheat, to baffle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science with an imagined sence, signification, and nature of words, and things, which the genuine and proper interpretation of them, will not admit, and the vulgar and received accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and use will not allow, but contradict; they who thus do, with a good conscience, shall go alone for me; the Lord keep me
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119323:16"/>
               <hi>in simplicity,</hi> which is <hi>godly sincerity,</hi> for I see not the help of your <hi>liberty</hi> one stone higher by <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> than the <hi>validity</hi> of your Ministry, but it may be the <hi>accumulated dignity</hi> thereof must make amends for all.</p>
            <p>Yet, Sir, I must confess, my sight is not so clear, as to see what lustre <hi>Lawn sleeves</hi> can adde to a <hi>lawful ordination,</hi> more than a Scotch Presbyter in a Black Coat. The truth is, Sir, I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</p>
            <p>That Re-ordination by a Bishop may more <hi>abstract from,</hi> than <hi>accumulate to</hi> the Dignity of your Ministry; so as to render it one <hi>iota</hi> more <hi>honourable in it self,</hi> or <hi>acceptable</hi> to the people, subjected to it. For, Sir,</p>
            <p>What is therein a <hi>Bishop</hi> that may be imagined to augment the Dignity of a Gospel-Ministry? Admit we that he is <hi>primus Presbyter,</hi> promoted <hi>honoris causa,</hi> into an higher degree; yet he must know, Ordination is an Act of his <hi>Presbytery,</hi> not <hi>priori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> the last, hath no <hi>intrinsecal power of ordination;</hi> and Christs Ordinance is not under the influence of his honour; it is full in its self; neither needeth, nor can receive accumulation from him, as I have before observed. It is not for the highest men to adde unto Gods heaps. When we have serued up <hi>Episcopacy</hi> to its height of honour, and debased <hi>Ministry</hi> to the meanest step of a Countrey Curate, yet, <hi>that</hi> must be acknowledged to be <hi>an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane order,</hi> but <hi>this</hi> Gods <hi>Ordinance,</hi> the oriency and efficacy whereof consists in <hi>Christ his institution,</hi> not <hi>his servants di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spensation; that</hi> hath no intrinsecal power, to conveigh the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Jesus Christ, as <hi>this</hi> hath. <hi>My Lord the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi> must be poor and plain <hi>Jack Presbyter,</hi> if he will ordain an Officer in Christ his Church; and in case of want, will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>meanest Presbyter</hi> hath as much Authority to conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate <hi>his Holynesse,</hi> as the <hi>Stateliest Cardinal</hi> in <hi>Rome:</hi> How then can this Honour accumulate to the Dignity of Ministry? It may indeed gratifie the fond Humour of such, who judge things by their sensible <hi>State and Pomp,</hi> not by their <hi>Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Spiritual Nature;</hi> and many times dishonour God by the Stately Representations of their own devises, which darken the Glorious Simplicity of His own Institutions: Yet, Sir,</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119323:16"/>
            <p>Supposing the priority of a Bishop to be an <hi>honourable piece of order adding lustre to ordination,</hi> the Question is,</p>
            <p>Whether it be <hi>worth, and can warrant the reiteration of Gods Ordinance,</hi> and solemn invocation of his holy Name? I believe <hi>Ordinations</hi> as <hi>Oaths,</hi> are prophaned, when vainly, triflingly, without weighty cause, on a meer punctilio of honour, they are <hi>reiterated,</hi> though to accumulate the honour of some circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, which would have been well added at the first, but now cannot be enjoyed without exposing Gods Ordinance to scorn, causing it to receive honour from men; whilst what hath been done in his Name, must be undone, that it may be dressed up in the bravery of mans invention, not Gods prescription: Right Reason will refuse to reiterate the <hi>essentials which conferre an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;</hi> for to accumulate the Dignity which any circumstance might have added; and shall Religion admit thereof? let good conscience judge. But, Sir,</p>
            <p>It is an enquiry (I think soon resolved) Whether the <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> which wanted this circumstantial punctilio of <hi>political civil honour</hi> (for the Classical Moderator maintained the Ecclesiastick Order) did not <hi>accumulate dignity</hi> by some more <hi>honourable cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances</hi> (in a near vicinity to the essentials of Ordination) of Gods own appointment, and adding much to the lustre of the Ministry conferred? Particularly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Election of the people;</hi> the Solemn (though silent) suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages of the whole Assembly <hi>highly esteemed,</hi> nay made <hi>essential</hi> by the Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and in the dayes of <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Though I could not tie the Keys of Christs Church at the Peoples Girdle, I think there is one ward in every Lock in Gods house that cannot open, (save by an Act of force) without the <hi>consensus plebis.</hi> I well know <hi>the ordering of Priests</hi> doth pretend to this, though it be done in a Chamber, or Prelates Chappel, some scores (if not hundreds) of Miles from the place of the Priests Relation, and where no man hath knowledge of him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Solemn, serious, and soul-humbling Fasting,</hi> in which Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainers, Ordained, and the whole Assembly, abstain from all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-comforts, <hi>enforcing prayer</hi> in the imposition of hands, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as was used by the Apostles and Church in their time. This circumstance (if I may so call it) doth shine with that brightness, that our Ordainers of Priests will pretend to it, and professe they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119323:17"/> observe it, though any day in any place (without any solemn se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of a day to that purpose) will passe this act,<note place="margin">See the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Book of the Consecration of Bishops, and ordering of Priests. Canons of 1603. Can. 31.</note> and at the best any <hi>Sunday</hi> or holy-day, (never allowed for fasting, nay, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicted by the Primitive and our own Church) is appointed for this work; and to palliate the neglect of this most sacred duty, it must be ordained, that Priests and Deacons be ordered on the four Sabbaths after the <hi>Ember-weeks,</hi> Superstitious Fasts, nay, mock-Fasts, being an abstinence from flesh to fish, without any regard to the nature of that <hi>soul-humbling, prayer-enforcing duty,</hi> which ever did in the times of the Apostles and primitive Church, (whom these men pretend to follow) and still ought to accompany the duty and very act of Ordination.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The imposition of hands by those persons who are known undeniable <hi>Officers of the Lord and his Church,</hi> enjoying an indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable <hi>intrinsecal power to ordain,</hi> being the chiefest and most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Cisterns and Conduits</hi> of all Ecclesiastical power, and creators of Episcopacy it self, and every Bishop that is an Officer in Christs Church, not the civil state; all which is disputable in our <hi>English Bishops,</hi> acting as Bishops (as the Antithesis to Presbyters in this debate doth suggest) being at most but civil Officers, and subjects of civil Honor, and so abstracted from their fellow-Presbyters, and Presbyterial Power, can add no more to Ordination than any other of his Majesties Lords, if by his Majesties command, joyned with a Presbytery in this act and administration.</p>
            <p>Unto these I might add the <hi>grave, solid, serious instructions, and solemn charge,</hi> which is given in Christ his Name and Authority to the ordained and People, who are to receive him, the which whilst the Prelatical Ordination doth pretend unto, is done in a most flat, formal, and perfunctory manner.</p>
            <p>Sir, On these considerations I dare appeal to the People, (the onely proper judge of this Dignity) to declare the Christian gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, authority, and splendor of Presbyterial Ordination, without a Chair of State, a Reverend Father in God, or Arch-deacon with his <hi>Reverend Father in God, I present unto you this man to receive the order of Priesthood</hi> (not admitted or in being under the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) or the like expressions of worldly state and pomp.</p>
            <p>And, Sir, the <hi>Re-ordination now ordinarily received,</hi> to accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late this pretended dignity, is <hi>darker</hi> than what is usual, and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our Law or Canons, being done in a <hi>private Chamber,</hi> or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119323:17"/>
               <hi>any</hi> (nay almost every) <hi>day</hi> of the week (if not month and year) by him who ordains out of <hi>poverty for profit,</hi> making a trade of making Ministers, which looks very like <hi>Simony</hi> (especally that forbidden by the antient Canons called the Apostles) passing <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con and Priest in one day,</hi> contrary to the Canons of our Church, and that without <hi>fasting</hi> antecedaneous or concomitant (I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most said or solemn Prayer) by a person enjoying the <hi>Title</hi> of a Bishop, and <hi>praeterea nihil,</hi> (and that among such fools as will give it) having been degraded, if not excommunicated and exil'd by both Church and Kingdom, of which he was a subject, and he out of his <hi>own Diocess,</hi> so as that his Authority is disputable, and by antient Canons his Ordination null, and so a Re-ordaining unto a Reordination; and that which is worst of all publishing under his hand and seal notorious falshood, <hi>viz.</hi> that the persons ordained have <hi>subscribed the Articles directed;</hi> which (if many lie not, whom I the rather believe, because I know the pretermission thereof hath brought much griest to his Mill) they did not do: and that he had <hi>ordained them according to the form and order appointed in the Church of England,</hi> when scarcely any thing thereof is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served. Sir, they that thus accumulate to the <hi>dignitie of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrie,</hi> must think their people are (under the foolishnesse of Preaching) made such fools, as to prefer a dark Lanthorn unto the bright Sun; and a supposed Bishop in Lawn sleeves unto an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Minister of Jesus Christ in a black Coat.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, it is to be feared, that the <hi>reflection of it</hi> will <hi>abstract</hi> more from the Bishops Re-ordination, then it can <hi>accumulate</hi> to the dignity of the Re-ordained Ministry: For, Sir, howsoever some may be willing to resolve it, Re-ordination cannot but <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent</hi> to the people that hear of it, brethren that fear it, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies who conclude it, <hi>a nullitie, or at least vanitie and material de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> in the first Ordination; all men say, <hi>what is once well done is twice done,</hi> and conceive what is <hi>twice done was not at the first well done. Oliver</hi>'s second investiture with the pomp of a <hi>Parliamentary Assembly,</hi> by the hands of a <hi>Speaker,</hi> and prayer of a <hi>Chaplain,</hi> did no little abstract from his first Instrument, and instalment in the presence of the Judges, Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> Officers of the Army, and other Gentlemen; and conclude a nullity of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and make Necessity the onely plea for his usurped actings. Nor can <hi>Oliver's</hi> Knights be re-Knighted by his Majesty,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119323:18"/> and men not conclude their first Knighthood vain.</p>
            <p>Let it, Sir, be remembred, that Ordination is the <hi>conferring an Office and Authority,</hi> and then whoever seeth it <hi>reiterated,</hi> avoid if they can a <hi>nullity</hi> in the first: Must not <hi>young Divines,</hi> who (by fancied pretended Antiquity) dream <hi>a Bishop is essential to ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> conclude it a Certainty, when they see the Ordained by Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters come to a Bishop to be Re-ordained? Will not the <hi>people,</hi> who observe the debate between Bishops and Presbyters, conclude the Presbyters in an error, when they see them renouncing their own principle by coming under the Bishops hands to be re-ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Will not the <hi>Papists</hi> soon pronounce a nullity on the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry of the Reformed Churches, who are without Bishops, when they see <hi>English</hi> Presbyters re-ordained by their Restored Bishops, though formerly ordained by the Presbyters? And however some <hi>Cassandrian</hi> re-ordainers may fallaciously pretend and profess <hi>their re-ordination to be meerly accumulative</hi> (redundant, super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, and needless) can any rational man conceive they intend not by it, and will shortly improve it, as an Argument of the nullity of the first Ordination without a Bishop? And judge it <hi>invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> an instance <hi>de facto</hi> being of more force with them, than the institution of God? They that clamour on the single case of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luthus his Presbyters</hi> (no way parallel to ours) and <hi>Epiphanius</hi>'s censure of <hi>Aerius</hi> his <hi>parity of Bishops and Presbyters,</hi> how will they boast and roare out the many Re-ordained <hi>English</hi> Presbyters at the first Ordained by the intrinsecal power of a Presbytery without a Bishop, and politically backed with the Authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</p>
            <p>Sir, well may our Re-ordainers declare their Re-ordination to be <hi>meerly accumulative,</hi> whilst it layeth heap upon heap unto confusion; being likely, yea certain to accumulate <hi>scandal</hi> to the Reformed Churches: <hi>stumbling</hi> to weak Christians and young Divines: <hi>suspicion</hi> of prophane and void administrations of Word and Sacraments; and so the loss of Church and Christianity it self; necessitating another <hi>Austin</hi> to come from <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>Englands fourth conversion: strength</hi> to the vain fancies, erronious Opinions, proud humours, <hi>Cassandrian</hi> design, and Oppressive rage of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates against others who dare not herein submit unto the Bishops Benediction: <hi>Strife and Endless Controversie</hi> about the divine right, superiority and essentiality of a Bishop to Gods Ordinance,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119323:18"/> in a Ministers Ordination; and so run us into the Labyrinth of <hi>suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession,</hi> so long Ravelled into, and never to be resolved: <hi>Scorn, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and contumely</hi> to Presbytery, Gods undoubted, authentick, and Primitive Institution, and the Church her chief, sure, never-fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pillar: and <hi>contempt and derision</hi> of the Ministry of the <hi>Reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,</hi> as seated in a man of levity, vanity, or perfidie, and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, cheating the Church with a <hi>false Commission;</hi> and dispensing Gods Ordinances by a <hi>fained Authority,</hi> Ruling Gods people by <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surpation;</hi> or rather prostituting their consciences and Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to the lust, pride, state, and pomp of a Lordly Prelate: these, Sir, are according to my little Reason, the large heaps naturally accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated by a Reordination; to which it is indeed a new act or accesse of new matter; they being filled up by other principles and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of error and prophanesse; and so it may be declared in truth to be <hi>accumulative,</hi> which otherwise is a <hi>vanity and falshood,</hi> whilest as we see it accumulateth nothing to the <hi>validity, liberty, or dignity</hi> of the Ministry of the Re-ordained; and certainly such a Declaration can never be a good <hi>salvo</hi> on which a good conscience may submit to be Re-ordained.</p>
            <p>Reverend Sir, your second <hi>salvo</hi> is no more significant, or lesse shameful and sinful than the first; supposing (what cannot rationally be supposed) that your Re-ordainers will admit you a liberty to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare at your Re-ordination <hi>that you neither do nor will renounce your Ordination received by the laying on of hands of the Presbytery with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Bishop,</hi> so as to charge that with <hi>vanity;</hi> and your administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (by the authority thereof) with <hi>iniquitie;</hi> but you will yet own that as <hi>valid;</hi> and by <hi>vertue thereof</hi> still exercise your Ministry; though to satisfie such as exact it, and to obtain your liberty you do thus submit to be <hi>Re-ordained;</hi> must not all that hear you, or of your profession, charge you with <hi>notorious fallacie and horrid hypocrisie?</hi> and your <hi>Re-ordainers</hi> themselves, laugh at your self-deceit; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man say to you <hi>quid verba audiam cum facta videam?</hi> What signifies this protest? doth he not really renounce his Ordination, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede from his office, and divest himself of authority, who thus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth up his Ministry, and anew passeth under this constituting invest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ordinance? Was it ever known in the Church that Ordination judged valid, was reiterated? is not the second act an actual and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal voidance of the first?</p>
            <p>It is well observed by the Reverend <hi>Hooker</hi> that great Oracle of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119323:19"/> the Church of <hi>England) They who have once received the power and Office of the Ministry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cclesiast. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cie, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Sect</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 411.</note>
               <hi>may not think to put it off and on like a Cloak as the weather serveth, reject and resume it as often, and in what manner themselves please;</hi> the which he judiciously brandeth to be a <hi>prophane and impious contempt of Gods Ordinance;</hi> and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther determineth, that although <hi>degradation doth utterly cut off the use and exercise of the Ministry,</hi> yet (as in separation of the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>after reconciliation and restitution to the former dignity there neither is, nor needeth a reiteration of the former knot;</hi> what should it avail the <hi>re-married</hi> to professe <hi>they will not renounce their former marriage?</hi> or <hi>Oliver</hi> at his <hi>Re-investiture</hi> to professe he was <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor before?</hi> Many by a subsequent act, charge themselves with <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannesse or usurpation;</hi> who will not call themselves <hi>Whores, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators or Ʋsurpers,</hi> modesty may interdict, a <hi>verbal owning of that guilt,</hi> which a reiterated action doth <hi>Reallize</hi> unto the spectators.</p>
            <p>Sir, in your case the Re-ordained must needs fall under <hi>reluctancie of conscience,</hi> and an apprehension that his <hi>Reordination doth charge vanity and usurpation on his past ministerial actings;</hi> otherwise whence comes his apollogetical protest? what needs such a contradictory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession? which amounts to thus much, <hi>I will not do what I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to do;</hi> I will not charge my self, or divest my self of that <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> which this <hi>renewed act</hi> doth charge upon me, and take from me, that it may give it to me again; think you, Sir, such a contrary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession can any way alter the nature of Re-ordination? if not; is it not most <hi>insignificant and sencelesse?</hi> a me<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r cheat to a mans self? and a frivolous blind to such spectators who will be blinded by an insignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant sound, not understanding the nature of the renewed act?</p>
            <p>Sir, I must he bold to say that Re-ordination with such a profession, is like the making oaths and promises with a profession of <hi>self-devised sences and salvo's,</hi> which are contrary to the Grammatical constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Logical Resolution, or genuine interpretation of the same: I have known some who would subscribe to be <hi>true and faithful to the Common-wealth of England as established without King and House of Lords,</hi> so far as it was consistent with the Word of God, and the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant;</hi> which were directly contrary therunto; and one who had thus suscribed, falling in with his Majesty at his march to <hi>Worcester;</hi> being taken by the <hi>Republicans,</hi> and tryed for his life, was charged with his <hi>Engagement,</hi> and perfidy in not keeping it, to which he pleaded the <hi>sence in which he subscribed;</hi> but was retorted on,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119323:19"/>
               <hi>The words will bear no such sence;</hi> and according to their genuine sence he was condemned and hanged, though as a Souldier quarter was granted him before, and it pleaded in bar to his tryal.</p>
            <p>I understand Dr. <hi>John Gauden</hi> (my known Antagonist) doth now profess he did swear the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> (from which he now absolveth himself and others) with a profession that his judgment was for <hi>Bishops and Episcopacy,</hi> (and his mind on a Bishoprick he might have added) and that he would endeavour to <hi>reform Episcopacy;</hi> and so swear this <hi>Covenant</hi> as far as it was consistent with his <hi>former Oaths, the Laws of the Land, and preservation of Episcopal Government;</hi> the express words of the Covenant being <hi>to extirpate Prelacy, that is to say, the Government by Arch-bishops, Bishops, their Chancellors, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Arch-deacons, and all other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Officers depending on that Hierarchy:</hi> which is a flat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: I am sure <hi>preservation</hi> and <hi>extirpation,</hi> are inconsistent; yea, Sir <hi>(Horresco referens)</hi> I hear of some, who, to be created Doctors, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d ined or reordained Ministers, or to get induction and instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to a good Benefice; have subscribed the Canonical Articles with this senceless salvo, <hi>Secundum Licentiam Rege Concessam,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to His Majesties late Declaration concerning <hi>Ecclesiastical af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs;</hi> which, only dispenseth with the <hi>act of subscribing,</hi> to such as in conscience cannot <hi>conform to the subscription required by the Canon,</hi> but maketh no interpretation of the <hi>Articles;</hi> and so their subscribing is a pure insignificant cheat; the doing of that by the <hi>Kings leave,</hi> which they were required to do before, and His Majesty indulged them to leave undone; the mention of which they foolishly fancy to be a <hi>nullify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their act,</hi> &amp; <hi>release of their obligation;</hi> but they will find it to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, when they come to be censured as Revolters after subscription.</p>
            <p>Sir, This kind of acting is apparently inconsistent with <hi>a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science;</hi> because <hi>irrational and irreligious;</hi> contrary to the nature of a man, a Christian, much more a Minister: For, Sir, it is a <hi>suspension of the judgement;</hi> yea, a forcible and violent stifling of <hi>Reason,</hi> and that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seretive power, with which every man is naturally endowed, and by which he ought to be Acted in every Action; whatever submission to a <hi>Judicium forense,</hi> Superiors may demand, Nature will teach us that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>individuum</hi> among men, ought to be Acted by his own <hi>judicium rationale,</hi> discretion and determination, and not <hi>halt between two opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> with strangers <hi>serve God and Ashtoreth,</hi> and with <hi>Israel,</hi> worship <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> and profess <hi>for the Lord;</hi> it is repugnant to <hi>mans nature,</hi> to cheat himself in an Action, by an interpretation directly contrary to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119323:20"/> of the Act, and Gods Ordinance: yea, this is repugnant to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>end of speech:</hi> the interpreter of the mind, unto the security, and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of others; which ought ever to make so certain a sound, as should comment on, not cloud, much less contradict the present Action.</p>
            <p>Sir, it is an apparent <hi>vile and abhominable hypocrisie</hi> to give a verbal gloss on that action which in its nature is expresly contrary thereunto: To act <hi>iniquity</hi> with a professed integrity, is most horrid, and may not be endured. It is a notorious <hi>mocking of God,</hi> to profess a preservati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Dignity of his Ordinance, in the very act of <hi>prostituting it,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a prophane contempt.</p>
            <p>If, Sir, this <hi>salvo</hi> can satisfie <hi>a good conscience,</hi> let us never blame the Jesuites mental reservation, or fallacious equivocation, whilst we assume the impudence of doing and professing <hi>openly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Becan.</hi> 5. <hi>Man. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov.</hi> 14. <hi>N.</hi> 4, 6. <hi>Oxford</hi> Reasons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Covenant. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.21. Pro. 30.20</note> what their modesty or subtlety (not honesty) doth more conceal, and so <hi>verifie</hi> the scandal (by them) cast on the Protestants, in special the Calvinists (of late spightfully applyed to Presbyterians) <hi>That they will swear and protest one thing in words, and in their own sence mean and act another:</hi> if this kind of acting may be admitted, what sin may not be safely committed, and meet with a present Apology? Who will not with <hi>Solomons</hi> adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous woman, <hi>wipe his mouth, and say, I have done none iniquity?</hi> or as the learned <hi>Mercer</hi> glosseth, <hi>Rem turpem verbis occultis &amp; honestis exprimere?</hi> Will not this build a Bridge on which a good conscience may pass to <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>holy orders,</hi> and subscribe to the Articles of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> so far as they are agreeable to the Word of God?</p>
            <p>Sir, Resolve your case, by a parallel case (not yet come upon us) and you will the better judge it. <q>Suppose the Anabaptists had prevail'd, and (possessing the Power of the Nation) Resolved, None should en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy <hi>liberty or dignity,</hi> in Church or Common-wealth, unless <hi>baptized in an adult estate;</hi> and therefore they require the present Possessors (baptized in infancy) to be <hi>rebaptized,</hi> or relinquish their enjoyments; the <hi>rebaptizers</hi> will (please fools so far, to) declare their <hi>rebaptization</hi> is <hi>meerly accumulative,</hi> and the rebaptized shall declare they do not <hi>renounce their former baptism:</hi> may a man with a good conscience, be thus rebaptized?</q> judge you. I know no difference between your case and this, s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve, that Baptism is a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and I am sure Ordination is a <hi>Sacred Ordinance of God,</hi> and no more to be prophaned than a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Sect</hi> 29. <hi>p.</hi> 246</note>Sir, I observe a passage in <hi>Hookers</hi> Ecclesiastical polity, which I have often thought worth the observation of our temporizing Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119323:20"/> who think (by good professions) to palliate their prophane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances, and preserve their credit: It is this; some Ministers not sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied to wear the <hi>Surplice,</hi> were by some men (more prudent than pious) perswaded to do it, and to prevent the danger of their peoples scandal, to profess publickly against it, which they accordingly did, making this profession, <hi>Brethren, our hearts desire is, that we might enjoy the full liberty of the Gospel, as in other Reformed Churches they do, elsewhere, upon whom the heavy hand of Authority hath imposed no grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous burden, but such is the misery of these our days, that so great happiness we cannot look to attain unto:</hi>
               <q>Were it so, that the equity of the Law of <hi>Moses</hi> could prevail, or the zeal of <hi>Hezechias</hi> be found in the hearts of those Guides and Governors under whom we live; or the voice of Gods own Prophets be duely heard; or the examples of the Apostles of Christ be duely followed, yea or their precepts be answered with full and perfect obedience, <hi>these</hi> Abhominable RAGS, POLLƲTED GAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS, MARKS and SACRAMENTS of IDOLATRY, which Power, as you see, constraineth us to wear, and conscience to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre, had long ere this day been removed both out of sight, and out of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory: But as now things stand, behold, to what a narrow strait we are driven! On the one side we fear the words of our Saviour, <hi>Wo be to them by whom scandal and offence cometh!</hi> And on the other side at the Apostles speech we cannot but quake and tremble, <hi>If I preach not the Gospel, wo be unto me!</hi> Being thus hardly beset, we see not any other remedy, but to hazard your souls the one way, that we may the other way endeavour to save them; touching the offence of the weak, therefore we must adventure it; if they perish they perish: Our Pastoral charge is Gods absolute Commandment; rather than that shall be taken from us, we are resolved to rake this filth, and to put it on, although we judge it to be so unfit and inconvenient, that as oft as ever we pray or preach so arrayed before you, we do, as much as in us lieth, to cast away your souls that are weak-minded, and to bring you to endless perdition: But we beseech you Brethren, have a care of your own safety, take heed to your own steps, that ye be not taken in those snares, which we lay before you; and our prayer in your behalf to Almighty God, is, That the poyson we offer you, may never have power to do you harm.</q> An hearty profession, and good warning to the people, but horrid iniquity, to make <hi>a choice of sin,</hi> though the least, and presumption, <hi>to tender Poyson with Prayer to God</hi> for prevention of its effect: Could this be made in faith? But observe Mr. <hi>Hooker's</hi> gloss upon this profession, <hi>Our people being accustomed to think that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119323:21"/> thing evil, which is under any pretence publickly reproved, and the men themselves worse which reprove and use it too, would conclude it was to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpose for them to salve the wound, by making protestations in disgrace of their own actions, with plain acknowledgement that they are scandalous, or by using fair intreaty with weak brethren: It cannot be endured to hear a man openly profess, he putteth fire to his Neighbours house, but yet so halloweth it with prayer, that he hopeth it shall not burn. It had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to have observed St.</hi> Basil<hi>'s advice both in this, and things of the like nature, Let him which approveth not his Governors Ordinances, either plainly shew his dislike, if he have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, str<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng and invincible reason against them, according to the true will and meaning of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; or else let him quietly, with silence, do that which is enjoyned: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience with profest unwillingness to obey, is no better than manifest dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.</hi> If, Sir, this learned man had been as rational, religious, and sound in other parts of his polity, as he is in this, he would have made me a forward Builder in his Ecclesiastical Fabrick; for I am convinced, that they who restrain <hi>piety</hi> by <hi>prudence,</hi> will find its forcible retort up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to their shame and sorrow.</p>
            <p>Reverend Sir, I have with all plainness answered your desire, and given my thoughts in your case of conscience; if in any thing I have mistaken you, or not made an Answer to what you expected, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in your next to intimate the defect; I shall (according to my poor ability) make a supply: I wish, Sir, you, and men in the like <hi>dilemma,</hi> may not deceive your selves in the state of your question: The ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Bishops essential to Ordination, is undoubtedly endeavoured as that which can best settle them in their rich and honourable seats, and suggests in them <hi>a divine superiority above Presbyters;</hi> in order whereunto the <hi>re-ordaining</hi> of men ordained by Presbyters without a Bishop, is (whatever is pretended, by whatever fallacy it can be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected) designed as a Declaration of the <hi>nullitie</hi> of their Ministry so ordained. Sir, zeal and sincerity are the only supports of Reformed Religion, most shamefully betrayed by the sinful compliances of some self-deceiving men; let it be your and my care to prepare for the Cross, and glory in it, and with due courage to bear witness to the least of the truths of the Gospel, on which depend the very <hi>being</hi> of the Reformed Churches, and <hi>enforcement</hi> of the Covenanted Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; <hi>committing our selves in all well-doing</hi> (as well as speaking) <hi>to him who judgeth righteously.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <hi>I am</hi>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The meanest of your brethren in<lb/> the great work of Gospel-Ministry,</hi>
                  <lb/> ZACH. CROFTON.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lond.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 26th. <hi>Febr.</hi> 1660/61</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>